Joan and Peggy Murray Papers, 1880-1969
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Joan and Peggy Murray papers
1880-1969
1911-1969
Murray, Joan, 1917-1942
MS 295
10 boxes (5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Collection consists of correspondence (1931-46); clippings; writings; memorabilia; photographs; and printed material documenting the lives of mother Peggy Murray, diseuse, and daughter Joan Murray, poet.
Florence Margaret (Peggy) Toaps Murray was born in Ottawa (date unknown). She toured Canada and England as a "diseuse" ("The Canadian [Yvette] Guilbert"), doing readings in accents, singing, etc. She took up painting at age 52, and at some point moved to Easthampton, Massachusetts. Her date of death is presently unknown. Her daughter, Joan Vincent Murray was born in London on 12 February 1917 during a World War I air raid. She spent her early childhood in England, and later attended schools in London, Paris, Ontario, and Detroit. Rheumatic fever injured her heart, and she was largely self-educated thereafter. She studied acting at several New York City schools and appeared in semi- professional plays. Her poems attracted the attention of W.H. Auden, who wrote the forward to one of her book of poems, published in 1947. She died of an infection in Saranac Lake, NY on 4 January 1942.
The collection consists of correspondence (1931-46); clippings; writings; memorabilia; photographs; and printed material documenting the lives of mother Peggy Murray, diseuse, and daughter Joan Murray, poet.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.
Search Terms
Murray, Joan, 1917-1942; Murray, Peggy; Actresses--Canada--Biography--Sources; Actresses--England--Biography--Sources; Dreier, Katherine Sophie, 1877-1952; Auden, W.H. (Wystan Hugh), 1907-1973; Poets, American--20th century--Biography--Sources; Murray, Peggy
Contents List
- Joan Murray
  - Rilke, Rainer Maria. Selected Poems, London, The Hogarth Press, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Murray, Joan. Poems. New Haven, Yale University Press, 1947. Edited by Grant Code. (Yale Series of Younger Poets)-contains hand written notes
    - Book of Common Prayer (Box 1)
    - Correspondence between Grant Code and W.H. Auden, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1931-42 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence re her final illness, 1941-42 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Tributes and reviews, 1947-18, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Photographs (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Writings and notes (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Biographical material (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Writings
      - Poems (Box 1)
        - Notes (Box 2, Folder 1)
        - Reviews (Box 2, Folder 2)
        - Proofs (Box 2, Folder 3)
        - True copies (Box 2, Folder 4)
        - Correspondence (Box 2)
          - Grant Code and Mary Newman, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
          - Grant Code and Helen Anderson, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 6)
        - Clippings, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Forward to A Faun Surmising by Grant Code, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Sway to the Clouds Swing to The Sun," dedicated to Joan, by Peggy Murray (sheet music) (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Typescripts of poems (Box 3)
  - Peggy Murray
    - Notebook (Box 4)
    - Poetry to reshape for publication (Box 4)
    - Study at conservatory (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - The studio (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Society about 1910 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Sketches from my life (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Dodging subs (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - The costume party (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - The escort (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Introductions (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Girlhood and school (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - The shoemaker (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Taxi ride to studio (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Debarkation (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Stan in London (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Whales (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Days at sea (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - The Mad Man's Monologue (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - The ship's concert (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Kipling: whale (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Drummond's poems and others (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - The Walkers (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Prose version (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Icebergs (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Fog (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - The agent (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Stan and his painting (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Beginning of romance with Stan (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Mrs. Allingham (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Stan's family (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Eastbourne (Box 4, Folder 29-30)
    - Secret marriage (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Maidenhead (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - 6 unlabeled folders and miscellaneous loose material, poetry, printed material, mss. Data for biography (Box 4)
    - Scrapbook, 1914-1916 (Box 5)
    - Notes (small spiral notebook) (Box 5)
    - Engagement book (Box 5)
    - Autograph book (Box 5)
    - Notecards of possibly books, articles read ?? (Box 5)
    - Love and Valor by Tom Hood (Box 5)
    - Heritage of Byzantium by Marcu Beza (Box 5)
    - Ever A Fighter:A Modern Approach To The Work Of Robert Browning by Dallas Kenmare (Box 5)
    - Little Journeys, Eminent Artists: Botticelli (Box 5)
    - 1 pair of earrings, locket with hair, pin, porcelain of Queen Elizabeth, and a scarf (Box 5)
    - folder of miscellaneous photographs, correspondence, prints and drawings, and notes. (Box 5)
    - "A New Musical Comedy Introducing Singing Chorus of Dancers". Ballet by Peggy Murray (Box 6)
    - History of the Isle of Mull,the Hebrides and the history of the Mac or McLeans (Box 6)
    - The St Laurence (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Sketches on my life for BBC (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - The poetry of the unicorn and specters, etc (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Scripts (Box 6, Folder 4-6)
    - Poetry (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous poetry, scripts, programs, printed material (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - L.Baindridge Crist: songs (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Seventeen wives (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Printed material (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - The French Visitor (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Family opposition to marriage (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous printed material and poetry (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Proposal in ... ? (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Sister's marriage (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - The telephone call (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Duplicates (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - The Spirit of the Brush translated by Shio Sakanishi (Box 6)
    - Little Books on Art: Holbein edited by Cyril Davenport (Box 6)
    - 2 loose photographs (Box 6)
    - Manilla envelope of poetry (Box 6)
    - Diaries, 1928, undated (Box 7)
    - Charles Dickens by Julian Symons (Box 7)
    - Margot Fonteyn by Gordon Anthony (Box 7)
    - A Confucian Notebook by Edward Herbert (Box 7)
    - The Snow Goose by Paul Gallico (Box 7)
    - Poetry (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Siklianos by Grant Code (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Photographs (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Cadenza (poetry, scripts, notes) (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Plays and poetry (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Poetry, notes, misc. photographs (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Photographs and notes (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - "History of the Isle of Mull" (2 notebooks) (Box 7)
    - Words, ideas, sketches for "A New Musical Comedy..." (Box 7)
    - Notes (blue notebook) may be part of above?? (Box 7)
    - Manilla envelope of correspondence to Peggy Murray (Box 7)
    - Aristotle On Poetry and Music (Box 7)
    - Peggy Murray's "bits and pieces" (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous photographs (Box 7)
- Oversized Materials
  - "The World's Need, A Play of Light"
  - Drawings, poetry (Box 7)
  - Photographs (Box 7)